And now it's time to talk about the
emergence and growth of the middle class
in the guilded age. And it's a saucy
one. So if you're ready to get them
brain cows milked, let's get to it.
Okay. Now, it's true, like I mentioned
in a previous video, that the wealthiest
industrialist only got richer during
this period. And the wealth gap between
them and the working class grew wider
and wider as time went on. However, as a
direct result of industrialization, a
distinct middle class grew and developed
during this period. And these middle
class folks made more money than the
working class, but less than the elite
industrialist. And that's why they were,
you know, in the middle. Now, to be
clear, the guilded age didn't exactly
give birth to the middle class because
if you've been paying attention, the
middle class really rose back in the
first half of the 19th century with the
rise of the market revolution. But there
were two main differences between that
first emergence of the middle class and
the guilded age middle class. First of
all, the earlier middle class was made
up of a small handful of professions
like doctors and lawyers and clergy and
business people. But the middle class
that emerged in the late 19th century
still included those professions, but
was predominantly made up of management
jobs created by industrialization. And
then second, the earlier middle class
was much smaller while the later middle
class was far larger and therefore had
much more of a social and cultural
impact of which I'll have more to say in
a moment. Oh, and by the way, if you
want note guys to follow along with this
video and all my videos, check the link
in the description. Anyway, if I have my
finger on the pulse of 21st century
teenage culture, and you know that I do,
then I'm sure you're asking this
question. But Heimler, what historical
developments necessitated the emergence
of a middle class? It's like I'm in your
head, right? Anyway, there were two
developments that created the occasion
for the emergence and growth of the
middle class. First, the nature and
structure of large corporations required
new management positions and clerical
workers. In other words, the bigger and
more complex these corporations became,
the more that they needed managers to
oversee the implementation and outcomes
of the company goals. And this reality
grew out of the scientific management
movement pioneered by Frederick Taylor.
And in its most basic form, tailorism
emphasized the efficiency of work above
all else and thus eliminated waste and
boosted productivity. And so, managers
filled needed positions like accountants
and purchasers and information
directors. And if you want a term for
that, and I know that you do, then
middle managers were what we would call
knowledge workers. They didn't work with
their hands or their feet. No, they
primarily worked with their thinkythinky
parts. So that means they didn't get
dirty when they worked and their hands
were softer than a baby seal's hind
parts after a proper shampoo. Therefore,
these middle managers wore suits to work
and white collars, which is why they
became known as white collar workers as
opposed to the laboring class who were
known as blue collar workers. And then
the second development that facilitated
the expansion of the middle class was
increased access to education. So, as I
just said, the bulk of the middle class
were knowledge workers. And as you may
or may not know, knowledge work
requires, you know, knowledge. And so,
it's during this period that we see a
flurry of new colleges and universities
opening up. And for that, we have big
daddy government to thank. And here's
what I mean. So, Congress passed the
moral act in 1862, which designated
about 140 million acres of federally
owned land, which states could sell in
order to fund public universities that
focused on agricultural and mechanical
skills. And as a result, 57 universities
were established throughout the United
States, thus expanding access to the
needed education to further facilitate
industrialization. And that's great and
all, but you didn't think that every
American got equal access to that
education, did you? Don't be crazy. And
so in 1890, Congress passed a second
moral act which was passed to combat
racial discrimination and education
against blacks in southern states. And
basically, the 1890 moral act gave
states two options. either abolish
racial discrimination in university
admissions or else use the funds to
establish separate universities for
black Americans. And I'd be willing to
bet a prize hog that you know exactly
which option the southerners chose.
Yeah, they chose the latter option and
used the moral funds to create all black
universities. Therefore, the second
moral act encouraged racial segregation
and education. But even so, it did
expand opportunities for black education
in the south by establishing several
historically black colleges and
universities like Tuskegee University
and Alabama and South Carolina State
University. And despite the persistence
of Jim Crow laws and the resulting
racial discrimination, a small but
significant black elite emerged as a
result of increased access to education.
This roster included folks like IdaB
Wells and Booker T. Washington and Web
De Boyce to only name a few. Anyway, the
point is all those complications aside,
colleges and universities were springing
up like mad and that led to the
expansion of the middle class whose work
mainly relied on their big brains. Okay,
so we've established what kind of work
the middle class did, but now let's
consider how their lives looked outside
of work. And to be clear, it was mostly
men in the middle class who worked while
their wives were consigned to domestic
duties. Because as you may or may not
know, that husband's sandwich ain't
going to make itself. Anyway, the main
differentiating feature of the middle
class was that they earned more
disposable income than the working
class. In other words, the middle class
could pay for all their necessities like
food and clothing and housing and still
have money left to spend. And that
reality led to two distinct features of
these middling folks. First, their extra
income led to an expansive growth of a
consumer culture among the middle class.
You see, for much of world history, many
people's identities were bound up in
what they made. For example, if Kevin
here was a metal worker, then his last
name would be Smith because a Smith is a
metal worker. So, literally, Kevin's
very identity is tied up in what he
creates. Like, Kevin is what he makes.
But the rise of a consumer culture
changed that formulation. So, here's
Kevin as a fancy middle manager in the
Guilded Age. And because he doesn't
really make anything with his hands, he
begins to tie up his identity in what he
buys. So, he's not Kevin Smith anymore.
He's Kevin Swell body cutter. that
doesn't roll quite as trippingly off the
tongue, but the point is the middle
class made enough money to distinguish
themselves from the working class by
what they bought. Anyway, there were
lots of ways that these middle- class
folks could spend their disposable
income, and I told you about mail order
cataloges in the previous video. So,
I'll tell you about department stores in
this one. So, prior to this, people
shopped in local stores because they
needed some kind of necessity like beans
or rope or whatever. In other words,
shopping was an errand. But department
stores like Marshall Fields in Chicago
were multi-storied and featured opulent
architectural details and you just felt
altogether fancy walking around and
shopping. And in that way, the Gilded
Age department store transformed
shopping from an errand to an
experience. And that experience for the
most part was aimed at middle-class
women who did the bulk of the shopping
in order to satisfy the requirements of
their class's obsession with conspicuous
consumption. But I should also mention
that by 1900, 21% of American women were
part of the workforce as well, at least,
you know, until they got married. They
refer to themselves as the new woman
because they railed against the gendered
norms of the day and focused on their
careers and it's almost hard to say rode
bicycles. And that last one led medical
professionals to issue a dire warning to
bike riding women about the development
of what they called bicycle face. I'm
not kidding about this. They said if a
woman rides a bike too often then their
face would become strained and pale and
permanent dark circles would form under
their eyes because women are fragile and
weren't made for such physical exertion.
to which every woman who had ever gone
into labor and given birth with no
medication was like, "Oh, sure. Hold my
hoops." But then the second feature of
middle class life was increased leisure
time. And I couldn't even begin to tell
you all the ways that they spent that
newfound leisure. So, let me just give
you two. First, vaudeville shows became
extremely popular among the middle
class, though the working class enjoyed
them from time to time as well. It was
essentially a stage show that combined
different acts like singing and dancing
and acrobatics or comedy and other
varieties as well. And then second,
folks began to frequent amusement parks
like Coney Island in New York. It was
the largest amusement park in the
country at this point, and it had rides
and games and hotels that promised to
fill Americans leisure time with
spectacle and fun. But here's where I
tell you that the Guilded Age was not
just a time for rich people to buy crap.
No. Despite the fact that on the whole,
wealthy industrialists had the
reputation of being hoarders of wealth
and filled with greed, some of the
wealthiest business people turned to
philanthropy. And this philosophy was
famously articulated by Andrew Carnegie,
who called it the gospel of wealth. The
idea was that it was the god-given duty
of the rich not to hoard their wealth
and pass it on to their children, but
instead they needed to invest their
money into society to produce a more
just and equitable future for the many.
However, to be clear, men like Carnegie
drew a hard line between charity and
philanthropy. You see, charity involved
handing out money to individuals and
families, and that was abhorentt to
Carnegie since he believed that hard
work ultimately resulted in wealth. So,
to him, if you're poor, that just means
you're lazy and you're getting what you
deserve. On the other hand, philanthropy
was the act of giving to society and
building institutions that offered
everyone opportunities to improve
themselves. And to that end, there were
two main ways that adherence to the
gospel of wealth invested their money in
society. First, they invested in
education. For example, Carnegie funded
the construction of about 1,700
libraries in the United States because
he believed that these kinds of
environments enabled average citizens to
better themselves by their own efforts.
And then John D. Rockefeller provided
the majority of funds required to open
the University of Chicago and over the
course of the rest of his life continued
to contribute millions to the
university. And then the second target
of their investment was the improvement
of urban environments. For example,
Biddy Mason was a woman born into
slavery but eventually gained her
freedom in California. There she became
an entrepreneur and gained a sizable
fortune. And feeling an impulse to
improve the urban environment for the
black community, she funded the
construction of the first African
Methodist Episcopal Church in Los
Angeles and helped establish the first
black elementary school in the city.
Well, all right. You can click here to
watch my other videos from unit 6, or
you can click here to grab my video note
guides, which are going to help you get
all the contents of this course firmly
crammed into your brain fold. I'm glad
you came around, and I'll catch you on
the flip-flop.